Guide to the Thomas M. Kerr Papers, 1945-2004 AIS.2004.17
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Thomas M. Kerr Papers
1945-2004
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Kerr, Thomas M.
AIS.2004.17
10 Linear Feet (8 boxes)
The papers of Thomas M. Kerr contain correspondence and subject files primarily related to his local leadership of the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) from 1962 to 1984. The files cover an extensive variety of subjects, including material on women's rights, civil rights, criminal justice, civil liberties, conscientious objection to selective service, Democratic Party politics, academic freedom, separation of church and state, and students' and teachers' rights.
Biography
Thomas M. Kerr (1919-2006) was born in Hackensack, New Jersey. He received his A.B. from Lafayette College in 1940 and his J.D. from George Washington University in 1950. After serving as an attorney for the anti-trust division of the U.S. Justice Department, he moved to Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania, to work for Westinghouse Electric Company in 1956. Kerr subsequently entered private practice and became chair of the Pittsburgh chapter of the ACLU from 1962 to 1964, and president of the ACLU of Pennsylvania from 1964 to 1984. During this period, he also served on the national board of directors of the ACLU and was active nationally in Americans for Democratic Action. Locally, Kerr provided legal counsel to the anti-war, civil rights, and women's movements. He was also engaged in a wide variety of cases involving criminal justice, civil liberties, and academic freedom. Kerr died on February 25, 2006, in Pittsburgh.
Scope and Content Notes
The papers of Thomas Kerr contain correspondence and subject files primarily related to his role as chair of the Pittsburgh chapter and president of the Pennsylvania ACLU from 1962 to 1984. The files cover an extensive variety of subjects, including women's rights, civil rights, criminal justice, civil liberties, conscientious objection to selective service, Democratic Party politics, academic freedom, de-criminalization of drugs, separation of church and state, and students' and teachers' rights. Also scattered among the correspondence are news clippings and releases; newsletters; letters to the editor; texts of speeches; meeting minutes; financial reports; and election results.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Previous Citation
Thomas M. Kerr Papers, 1945-2004, AIS.2004.17, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Acquisition Information
Gift of Thomas M. Kerr in July 2004.
Related Material
American Civil Liberties Union, Pittsburgh Chapter Records, AIS.1997.16, Archives & Special Collections, University of Pittsburgh Library System
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into four series:
Series I. American Civil Liberties Union, Pittsburgh Chapter Correspondence, 1962-1967
Series II. American Civil Liberties Union of Pennsylvania Correspondence, 1967-1978
Series III. General Correspondence, 1956-1971
Series IV. Subject Files, 1945-2004
Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Protest movements -- Pennsylvania; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; Academic freedom -- Pennsylvania; Church and state -- Pennsylvania; Criminal justice, Administration of -- Pennsylvania; Civil rights -- Pennsylvania; Draft resisters -- Pennsylvania; Drug legalization -- Pennsylvania; Pro-choice movement -- Pennsylvania; Race discrimination -- Pennsylvania; Segregation -- Pennsylvania; Selective conscientious objection -- Pennsylvania; Social action; Sex discrimination against women -- Pennsylvania; Students -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- Pennsylvania; Feminism -- Pennsylvania; Correspondence; Lawyers -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.); Pennsylvania; American Civil Liberties Union. Pittsburgh Chapter -- Records and correspondence; Kerr, Thomas M. -- Records and correspondence; Democratic Party (Pa.); American Civil Liberties Union of Pennsylvania -- Records and correspondence
- American Civil Liberties Union, Pittsburgh Chapter Correspondence, 1962-1967; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series contains internal organizational correspondence primarily related to Kerr's service as chair of the Pittsburgh chapter of the ACLU. It encompasses a broad range of topics, including fair housing, public school de-segregation, capital punishment, rights of the accused, employee loyalty oaths, censorship, academic freedom, student rights, school prayer, freedom of speech, and the abolition of the U.S. House Committee on Un-American Activities. Also scattered among the correspondence are news clippings, newsletters, financial reports, and meeting minutes.
  - Correspondence, 1962-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1-24)
- American Civil Liberties Union of Pennsylvania Correspondence, 1967-1978; II.
  This series contains internal organizational correspondence primarily related to Kerr's tenure as president of the ACLU of Pennsylvania. It covers an extensive variety of topics including, women's rights (the Equal Rights Amendment, sex discrimination and abortion rights), civil rights (fair housing, public school de-segregation, racial discrimination in employment), criminal justice (capital punishment, rights of the accused and the right to a fair trial), civil liberties (employee loyalty oaths, censorship and FBI surveillance), conscientious objection to selective service, and academic freedom. Also scattered among the correspondence are news clippings, press releases, meeting minutes, budgets, and election results.
  - Correspondence, 1967-1970 (Box 1, Folder 25-36)
  - Correspondence, 1970-1978 (Box 2, Folder 1-24)
- General Correspondence, 1956-1971; III.
  This series contains personal correspondence primarily related to Kerr's law practice and political activities. It covers a wide variety of topics including the 1960 Kennedy presidential campaign, censorship, conscientious objection to selective service, civil rights, criminal justice, fair housing, affirmative action in the construction trades, school integration, students' rights, and FBI surveillance of political activists. Included in this correspondence are copies of sixteen letters to the editor from 1966 to 1970 and texts of nine speeches from 1966 to 1968.
  - Correspondence, 1956-1965 (Box 2, Folder 25-40)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1-23)
- Subject Files, 1945-2004; IV.
  This series contains subject research files primarily related to Kerr's law practice and public speaking engagements. It spans a broad range of topics, including school integration, abortion rights, affirmative action in the construction trades, capital punishment, censorship, rights of mentally ill, selective service, fair housing, rights of the accused, de-criminalization of drugs, separation of church and state, and the rights of students and teachers. Also included are some files on Kerr's academic work at Carnegie Mellon University and Point Park College.
  - Abortion, 1966-1974 (Box 3, Folder 24-25)
  - Academic Freedom in Secondary Schools, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1970-1974 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Black Community, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Black Construction Coalition, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Brown v. Board of Education, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Campisi, Carmello Case File (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Capital Punishment, 1965-1985 (Box 3, Folder 32-33)
  - Carnegie Mellon University, 1972-1979 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Carnegie Mellon University, Program for Executives, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 35-36)
  - Censorship, 1960-1969 (Box 3, Folder 37-38)
  - Centerville Clinics, Incorporated, Mental Health and Mental Retardation Program, Fredericktown, PA, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Circle Program, Pittsburgh Public Schools, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Civil Commitment of the Mentally IL, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Civil Liberties and the American Civil Liberties Union, 1967-1975 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Corporal Punishment, 1965-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Draft Deferment Case Letters, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Drugs, 1967-1972 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Dwelling House Building and Loan Association, 1968-1976 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Dwelling House Savings and Loan Association, 1973-1976 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Federal Crime Insurance Program, U. S. Department of Housing and Urban Development, 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Home Rule Charter for the People of Pittsburgh, Discussion Draft, September 1973 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Law Enforcement and the Rights of the Accused, 1963-1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Lowenstein, Al, U.S. Senate Campaign, 1973-1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Malone, Thomas Case File, August 20, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Non-Heartbeating Organ Donors, 1991-1993 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Non-Profit Bail Bonding Corporation, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
  - Oskoui, M. Case File, 1972-1976 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Pennsylvania Program for Women and Girl Offenders, Inc., 1971 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Point Park College, 1964-1975 (Box 4, Folder 17-18)
  - Prayer and Bible Reading in the Public Schools, 1958-1965, 1982, 1991 (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
  - Pre-trial Justice Project, American Friends Service Committee, 1968-1971 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Retention Committee, Retreat State Hospital, Hunlock Creek, PA, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Rights of Children, 1971-1975 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Rights of Students in Private Institutions, 1961-1966, 1969-1981 (Box 4, Folder 24-26)
  - Rights of Teachers and Students in Secondary Schools, 1969-1972 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Selective Service, 1968-1972, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 28-29)
  - Senate Bill 1, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Singer, Nathan Case File, 1945-1976 (Box 4, Folder 31-39)
  - Students' Rights, 1963-1969 (Box 4, Folder 40-42)
  - Unitarian Church, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Wage-Price Freeze, August 1971 - January 1972 (Box 5, Folder 2-3)
  - Watergate, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Welfare Rights, 1965-1969 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Civil and Labor Rights Articles (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Elaine Mittleman, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Personal Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Allegheny Bar Association Memorial Service for Marjorie Hanson Matson, Esq. Eulogy by Kerr, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence with Carnegie Mellon University (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Home Rule Charter Draft, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Research on Ethics in City Government (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Manuscript regarding Presidential Impeachment (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Carnegie Tech Ideas, Fall 1966 (Box 6, Folder 10-11)
  - Carnegie Tech, Fall 1965 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Carnegie Tech (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Zimbabwe 8 (Box 6, Folder 14-15)
  - Ingersoll-Rand and Flow International Corporation Merger, 1994 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - City of Pittsburgh Personnel Appeals Board, 1989 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - City of Pittsburgh Personnel Appeals Board, 1980-1985 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - City of Pittsburgh Personnel Appeals Board (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Lawsuits against Cities as Employers (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Lillian Roberts and William Terrell v. City of Pittsburgh (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Ray Wolfgang Appeal, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - David M. Stangl v. City of Pittsburgh, 1990 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - City of Pittsburgh Personnel Appeals Board, 1984-1990 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Gloria Novak v. City of Pittsburgh (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - City of Pittsburgh Personnel Appeals Board Correspondence, 1984-1989 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Kerr Interview Transcripts, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 9-15)
  - Kerr Obituaries and Articles (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - City of Pittsburgh Personnel Appeals Board Cases (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence with Melanie Smith, November 19, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - "The New People", Thomas Merton Center, May 1984 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - "Mr. Civil Liberties" Dinner Honoring Kerr, October 25, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Atlantic City Casino Articles (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1993 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Teaching Materials, 1984-1993 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Freedom of Speech and Expression (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Michael T. Newell v. City of Pittsburgh Civil Service Commission, 1991 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Contact Lists (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Personal Correspondence, 1990 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, Greater Pittsburgh Chapter, Inc. v. City of Pittsburgh (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Hate Speech (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Free Speech and Press, 1992 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Presidential Commemorative Print, 1995 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Clippings, 1992-1993 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - Complaint of Judicial Misconduct, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Letter to Working Assets Funding Service, August 1988 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1989-1994 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Clippings, Mid-Atlantic County, July 1994 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Thomas Paine (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - ACLU Reports (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Mt. Lebanon Committee and Voting, 1964 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Allegheny County Democratic Committee (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Kerr Court Documents (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Americans for Democratic Action, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Baptist Homes, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Labor and Civil Liberties, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Grand Jury Abuse, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 28)
  - George Countz v. Children's Hospital and Servicemaster Industries, Inc., 1979 (Box 8, Folder 29)
  - American Civil Liberties Union, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - University Relations with Intelligence Agencies (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1970s (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Freedom of the Press (Box 8, Folder 33)